which is a humanitarian aid for the Moscow
office.
I will show you how it works.
I will show you the video.
There's a lot of very brave and
extraordinary work that goes on around the
world from people who the public don't
really know very much about.
Politicians and society tends to be rather
cynical about journalism, but I see
enormous bravery, enormous challenge,
great courage going on to surface things
that the public really needs to know
about.
Journalists go towards danger when others
move away.
Journalists have to get involved with all
sides of the conflict in order to get the
story.
It takes a very fearless journalist to get
up every day and say, you know what, I'm
determined to continue my profession, even
though I
may have to spend the rest of my life
looking over my shoulder.
I
I came here in 2003.
I came to cover the US-led invasion.
I got here about three weeks before the
bombing campaign started and I stayed for
the next couple of years working on and
off.
I came because I thought the war was going
to to be covered pretty heavily in the
Western media from the
position of embedded journalists.
going to take any risk at all.
I'd rather take the risk making a story
that wasn't being told.
And I was concerned that the Iraqi
perspective would be neglected.
So I came and stayed in Baghdad and worked
in Baghdad instead of working embedded
with the US military.
It used to be that you could do a mix of
both.
I tried to keep it 50-50 so that I saw the
war from the soldiers' point of view and I
saw the war from the
local Iraqis' point of view.
Journalists play this vital role as sort
of an outside presence, an independent
person to sort of see how this war is
being conducted.
If you want to get to some of these
stories, you have to take the risks of the
people who are living through
the same thing.
And sometimes that means risking torture,
risking kidnapping, risking death.
I faced it.
Tremendous amount of danger.
I was shot at several times.
My car still bears the marks of bullets.
I was chased several times.
I got messages, letters taped on the
outdoor of my house.
As the militants went from using us to
reach the Western audience to just simply
lumping us in with troops and foreigners
as the enemy, we had to start...
Bedding with the troops, that was the
safest option.
That option that used to be viewed as most
dangerous was now the least worst option.
But when you travel with troops, you face
the same risks.
We wanted to go out with troops on
Memorial Day.
This was four months after ABC News anchor
Bob Woodruff had been hit by an improvised
explosive device, and he was still
recuperating from a brain injury.
What was supposed to be a routine shoot
lasting a couple of hours ended in
horrible
tragedy.
We ended up parked on a residential side
street, dusty, quiet, just about
deserted, and we got out of our vehicles.
Paul Douglas and James Brolin were filming
in our direction.
Turns out the insurgents were watching.
They command detonated an approximately
500 pound car bomb through all of us.
It killed James, our sound man, instantly.
Left Paul fighting for his life.
He did not make it.
He died at the scene.
Killed the captain and his translator
instantly.
Left me fighting for my life along with
four other.
Soldiers.
I technically died five times on the
operating table.
I had both femurs shattered, shrapnel to
the brain, both eardrums blown out.
I was burned from my hips to my ankles,
but worst of all my femoral artery was
cut.
So I bled out more than half my blood they
estimate.
The other folks with me were equally
horribly injured.
So it was a handful.
For the surgeons to try to salvage.
Kidnapping was and is a very real problem
in Iraq.
Criminal gangs, militias are roaming
around, finding ways to extort money.
This is why we've had doctors, academics,
lawyers.
a whole lot of Iraq's intelligentsia just
flee the country because they're at grave
risk of being kidnapped.
Anyone is at risk who can fetch a better
ransom.
You have to be thinking, okay, it doesn't
matter that I'm a reporter.
Now to them, I am a Westerner with a
potential big price tag on my head.
We went to do a report with Hussein, the
driver, at the University of Baghdad,
where the
residents of a city were being bombarded
by the US, the city of Fallujah.
We did our interview, we got into a car,
we got out of the
university.
When another car stopped us, and some guys
with Kalashnikovs got us out of the car...
It's true that you really feel like you've
passed the other side of the mirror.
I remember I was in this car that was
taking us, so we were taken off.
And I saw through the window the life that
was going on for people.
People in the cars next door, with a guy
smoking, his wife, people putting on the
radio.
There is a lot of bottling in Baghdad, so
we were doing well.
And I knew that I was already in this car,
in another world.
It was over, there was no way to stop it.
It's even weirder because there are a lot
of checkpoints.
We passed a checkpoint and I was
like, Hey, you, get down so we don't see
you.
We crossed the
mirror.
I'm a journalist in Liberation.
Please, help me.
My health is very...
Negotiations with hostages are happening.
We were locked in a cell, we didn't see
anyone.
We were in the dark, we had very little to
eat, we didn't wash.
So we had an animal life.
We were chained on the ground, so it was
really that life.
I ask especially Mr Didier Julia, the
French deputy.
Please Mr Julia, help me, it's urgent.
When I was a hostage in the...
In the place where we were detained, there
were 13 other people who were not
journalists.
There was one journalist for 13 citizens.
We are never the only apparent face, I was
going to say, of a repression that
generally affects everyone when it comes
on us.
You know, as dangerous as it might seem
sometimes in a place like that, you know,
it's unstable where the government's
really out of control or
there's a lot of fighting and insecurity.
If you make sort of friends who can show
you the way and give you some support
locally, then it's
not as bad as it seems.
In fact, I often felt like I was sort of
protected by the people around me as best
as anyone could be.
The basic rule is that you are only as
good as the local journalist you're
working with.
They are by far the most important
decision you'll make.
They understand what's happening on the
ground in a way you never can.
If you wanted to be a good journalist in
Iraq, you had to risk your life.
Other way you can't do it.
We risked our life to get the story, and
it was worth it.
I really believe there's something called
ground truth that journalists get when
they go into a place, talk to local
people, and they see with their own eyes
what is
happening, and there are facts that they
can convey.
As you may have heard, a Reuters
television sound man was killed today
while driving in Baghdad.
He was killed by U.S.
soldiers, and a cameraman was wounded.
Unfortunately, this kind of thing is
alarmingly common.
The Geneva Convention, of course, means
that civilians can't be targeted, and
journalists are, by definition, civilians.
We have had people killed.
It is really because the military says
they cannot tell the difference of a
journalist doing his work on the
battlefield and someone who is on the
battlefield for nefarious reasons.
And so then the Geneva Convention for all
the protections that it grants civilians
does not help the journalist in the field.
I do not believe that the military is
anti-journalist.
I do believe that the military is facing a
very different kind of battlefield, where
you don't know who's a friend and who's an
enemy.
It's a very frightening place for
journalists and for soldiers.
About one third of the journalists who get
killed, which is about a thousand over the
last two decades, one third of them are
killed in
armed conflict.
The actual problem in terms of numbers is
really on the local level.
That's where most of the journalists get
killed, not foreign correspondents, local
journalists.
Particularly in the case of Iraq, we've
seen more of our colleagues locally
killed.
They live there.
The front line, if you like, is outside
their front door.
AP doesn't have people parachuting in from
outside.
We have people who live and work in those
countries.
We feel that it's important to have folks
who live in a place explain it to the
world.
In April of 2004, Bilal Hussein, a
photographer for the Associated Press in
Fallujah, was picked up by the
military, which believed that he was
working for insurgents and held him for
what ultimately was two years without
charges.
During the US Marines siege of Fallujah as
they were trying to drive the insurgents
out of Bilal State, it's
his native city, he took a lot of pictures
of insurgents fighting and lots of other
scenes of fighting
and destruction of the citizens there.
At the time that was very controversial.
And there was a lot of unhappiness that AP
was showing both sides of the fighting.
Different people in those situations,
whether it's the U.S.
military or the contracting companies or
the locals or a resistance group or
whatever, are going to all perceive us
in their own ways, and usually that means
with suspicion and basically seeing us as
a problem.
It did not stop us because that was the
norms at the time.
I didn't know, I definitely didn't know
better.
I thought it comes, it's a package.
Fulfilling the dream of, you know, being a
mouthpiece for the Iraqis and getting the
danger
that comes with it.
In recent and ongoing conflicts like Iraq
and Afghanistan, the highest death toll,
if you like, is indigenous journalists.
Particularly in the case of Iraq.
We've had a black vehicle, surrounded
right to the north of the wall.
We've lost colleagues who were local
journalists, filming alongside or close to
insurgents.
We've got a target 15 coming at you.
On the battlefield, in the heat of the
moment, someone who looks different from
the
model of a foreign correspondent is even
more at risk.
Because even if he is carrying a camera,
even if he is carrying a tripod, the
assumption seems to be that they could be
hostile.
That's a weapon.
What happened in 2007 to the two war news
journalists in Iraq was a terrible tragedy
and one that was brought
home to all of us when we saw the footage
that WikiLeaks released.
And I think that really brought home the
horror of modern war and why it is so
dangerous.
Yep, he's got a weapon too.
Hotel 26, Crazy Horse 185 to 6 individuals
with AK-47s.
Request permission to engage.
What you had there was Apache helicopters
firing on a group of people from at least
500 meters away,
maybe a couple of kilometers away.
You have the assumption that everyone in
that group is of a type.
You have the assumption that because there
were weapons in that group, that everyone
in that group was armed and somehow
dangerous.
It became just a terrible tragedy that the
gunships fired on those people.
Our correspondents were killed along with
others.
We need answers to the questions about how
these situations happen.
We've engaged and will continue to engage
very actively with the authorities because
we don't take for granted that people just
happen
to be in the wrong place at the wrong
time.
They were walking with a group where there
were arms.
Now, in 2007, in Baghdad, that was
extremely...
common.
Everyone was walking around with arms.
But it became clear in the course of
investigating this that because they were
walking with this group, they were assumed
to be
hostile.
So we changed our rules and said, don't go
anywhere near anybody who is carrying a
weapon.
Now that makes it more difficult to do
your job as a journalist, especially in a
place where everyone is armed, but we felt
it
was a necessary precaution to take.
We were invited to an interview in
November of 2008 with a Taliban commander
just outside of Kabul, the capital of
Afghanistan.
The local journalist I was with had
interviewed this guy before.
He had done the interviews with these two
European journalists, and he had not done
anything.
And so they had this relationship, and he
felt it would be okay.
The issue of being taken hostage is a very
tricky one.
I mean there are conventional ways to, if
you like, avoid being a target.
But at the end of the day, if someone's
determined to take you hostage, then
that's going to happen.
We were told to drive to a meeting point
where we would meet these men who would
take us to this interview.
We rounded a corner and there was a car
blocking the road and these two Taliban
guys rushed up to our vehicle.
It didn't seem real at first.
We thought there was some confusion.
We hoped this was sort of a rough
introduction for our interview.
But it became very clear that wasn't true.
The key aspect of David's kidnapping was
most of the drama was played out in
Waziristan, which is the absolute bastion
of
the armed militant groups of the jihad in
Afghanistan.
The initial demands in my case were for
$25 million in cash and the release of 15
prisoners from Guantanamo Bay, Cuba.
There's no kind of clear rules on what to
do in a kidnapping.
And, you know, we survived, so I guess we
did the right thing.
But the idea that these militants are
going to somehow have a sort of reasonable
way of resolving the case
doesn't apply.
And we spent the next seven months in
captivity in north and south Waziristan,
shuttled from house to house.
And we were able to finally escape from
captivity in June of 2009.
And we made it to a Pakistani military
base.
And then we're allowed to go home.
The people that are most vulnerable to
kidnapping are the local reporters who are
doing very valuable
reporting in their own locality.
They are very, very much at risk.
There are some differences between the
threats to the national journalists and
the international journalists.
In terms of the perceived rewards,
somebody who's conducting a kidnapping,
they expect to get more out of it
if they get hold of an international
journalist.
But of course, if they just want to be
able to pick up a national journalist,
then probably nobody will come after them
and they don't have to perceive any
particular
threat of law enforcement action.
I am from Helmand.
I am a member of the Taliban.
I am a member of the
Taliban.
I am a member of the Taliban.
I don't know if it's a good idea or not.
I've been detained twice but I did feel
that going into Bosnian Serb territory and
being arrested there was
worth it.
Journalist restrictions were simply that
we were not allowed into Bosnian Serb
territory without an escort.
I felt that they were hiding, you know,
this evidence of thousands of people
dying.
I went to checkpoints and said I was
simply driving through Bosnian Serb
territory when in truth I was trying to
find these graves.
Those stories helped prove that 8,000 men
and boys were executed in Srebrenica.
A Bosnian Serb watchman saw me and
arrested me at the site.
And I was held for 10 days.
I was treated well, I was never beaten,
but they were convinced I was a spy.
I think my kidnapping in Bosnia was
basically about controlling the message.
They sort of kept denying that they had
carried out these executions.
Right before I was released, they had me
do an interview with Bosnian Serb TV where
I said I found no mass graves.
You know, it was a false statement, but I
was desperate.
I am very happy to be in Belgrade and very
grateful to the assistance of the Serbian
government in getting me here.
And it's a great relief for me to be able
to report to the Serbs.
When journalists stop going to these
places, the militants that are terrorizing
civilians, they win.
The governments that are oppressing
opposition groups, they win.
Our job is to report the world and to tell
the rest of the world what's happening and
to shine light in the darkest corners of
the world.
But we have to go on working very hard to
find the right way of doing that, the safe
way of doing that, that doesn't put
journalists and news teams' lives
unnecessarily at risk.
The president is a liar The president is a
liar
Why can anyone really think that our
calling as journalists is any less
important than the calling of a soldier?
I don't believe it is.
The sooner we understand and manage that,
the sooner we're actually going to come up
with safety policies that are really
effective.
A journalist has to be concerned about all
the contingencies that could arise from
landmines, to the possibility of
crossfire, to the possibility
of incoming mortars, to military forces
simply changing sides.
So a journalist needs a certain level of
combat awareness training.
as well as emergency first aid.
When the challenge started, I don't really
remember much after that.
There were a couple of close-ups.
And then we took...
I took a direct hit somewhere.
I was injured in the leg.
I think my colleague Marie-Kelvin is dead,
and Remy also is dead, as far as I know.
I don't know much at the moment.
As long as people are fighting each other
and killing each other and doing so in the
acquisition of power
or territory or, you know, a point of
view, journalists have to be there.
We have seen a rise in this culture of
impunity in some of the world's most
dangerous countries, not talking about war
zones now, but countries like
Mexico, where to kill a journalist is easy
censorship.
So journalists who make themselves
awkward, who do investigative work, who
get on the wrong side of particular
crime gangs or even particular political
divisions, make themselves vulnerable.
And we've seen that rise inexorably again
over the last decade.
You feel a certain insecurity, right?
Because it's dangerous to be a reporter
here in Mexico.
International journalism organizations
have said that it's more dangerous to be a
journalist in Mexico than in Iraq itself.
What you hear are gunfire shots, rifle
caliber, and there is also even
stronger sound than is happening on this
border of Reynosa.
The confrontation between federal forces
and what is practically some
organized cell of the military.
Unfortunately, in many cases in these
regions, authorities are co-opted by
criminal
organizations.
The influence of the cartels in many of
these areas is huge over law enforcement,
politicians, and state prosecutors.
And in most cases, these people are in
charge of investigating these crimes.
Cartels cannot exist without the help of
the state.
The police are the ones who give them a
way, the ones who stop investigating, the
ones who provide them with vehicles, the
ones who provide them with
logistics.
And that's what affects journalists at
this moment.
There are people who benefit from crime,
either drug barons or politicians, who
want to
send out a very strident signal to people
in our profession.
They're targeting investigative reporting.
They're targeting journalists who get up
every morning and want to spend time on
investigating corruption.
Fear is one of the overriding
characteristics affecting journalism in
Mexico.
Drug cartels have been basically
conducting war against journalists, as
well as others in the community.
Pursuing what was not merely my job but my
passion, I exceeded sheer reason on many
occasions.
So it often happened that in trying to
capture the best image or dig up a scoop,
I crossed the line into
danger.
In 2006, I received reliable information
that several journalists were named on an
organized crime hit list because of their
reporting on the Juarez drug worse.
My sword told me I wasn't that lazy.
I was doing some investigation related
with these abuses, human rights abuses for
militaries, but at the same
time this incident happened at the
massacre of the rehab center.
So I got information that witnesses said
that at least one big truck with soldiers
blocked the road to help the hitmen to be
at the rehab center and kill these
people.
with these two investigations going side
by side.
I started to notice that I had been
followed.
One day my wife, she went back home and
outside of his minivan,
she noticed that another minivan who was
following her parked just outside of the
house.
There's two men in the minivan.
One of the men took out his arm and
pointed like this.
This moment is when you understand that
your family, now they are in your
danger.
We have a phrase, it's quite common among
the police officers in Mexico.
They say that the heart and your stomach
gives you good advices.
So you have to learn to listen to them.
So you feel that something is wrong.
I can't explain it, how do you feel or...
When do you feel that something is strange
there?
So that's when I start to say, OK, I need
to leave.
According to CBJ research, more than 85%
of crimes against journalists go unsolved.
It's a huge problem which in many cases
perpetuates a climate of fear and
intimidation
where journalists and media are wide open
to attacks.
Impunity is a green light for those who
attack journalists in places around the
world.
I've been doing this job for over 20
years.
It's my passion and I have to keep
going.
I can't stay silent about what's going on.
Intimidation goes the whole scale.
I think you have to look on a case-by-case
basis whether the journalist is simply
afraid of losing his livelihood or whether
that
journalist is afraid of losing a limb or a
family member or his life.
And all these things have happened.
All these things are happening.
All these things are very much real for
people in the journalistic community.
Usually, they call you, they send you a
message through some...
Even for a journalist, another journalist,
or a friend, or a lawyer, they call you
and they say, you know what, you need to
stay out of this area.
In Tijuana, in the late 80s, early 90s,
the Arellano-Felix brothers were
doing business in an open way, they were
recruiting young people from society in an
open way.
Don Jesús Blanco Ornelas was doing
research on organized crime.
And when Blanco Ornelas identifies this
group as criminals or drug traffickers who
are taking over the streets of the
city, he starts pointing them out.
And he forces the authorities to
investigate.
The Arellano Felix brothers kill
Blancornelas, as a result of what we had
published in the weekly newspaper.
They kill Luis Valero, who was his
assistant and driver.
And Don Jesus miraculously survives.
The Don Jesus truck had more than 80
bullet impacts.
Instead of the events of the attack, one
of the hitmen is killed.
In fact, the one who was leading the group
of murderers.
So, in our investigations, we realize that
this person belonged to the Logan
neighborhood of San Diego and served in
the Arayano-Felix cartel.
So, it was the main league to give to the
intellectuals of the crime.
Why, if we know that the leaders of the
Cartel, Arayana Félix, attacked the life
of Don Jesús Blanco Ornelas,
why aren't they being judged for that
crime?
Not many media, despite the fact that drug
trafficking is getting stronger and more
terrible in Mexico and is causing
more harm to Mexican society, dare to
investigate drug trafficking, organized
crime.
Precisely because of the consequences.
What
happened?
What is the problem?
What happened?
Calm down In late July, four journalists
were kidnapped.
Two of them worked for national TV
stations.
And as a demand for the release, the
cartel said that the national TV must
broadcast some videos showing the other
cartel in collusion with federal
authorities.
So the drug war in Mexico is not only
fought in the streets, it's also a war for
the
control of information.
And there are indications now that the
cartels are trying to influence the
information agenda more widespread.
Cartels are telling publishers, editors
and reporters what they can publish or
what they can't
publish.
The sense of impunity against press is
high now.
Many people who can pay for kill a
journalist, maybe some of them are
thinking in killing a journalist because
it looks like nothing is going to happen.
I think they have a double purpose.
One is to...
Shut up this person to eliminate this
person as well as to send
the message to other journalists.
This is going to happen if you don't
follow my rules.
In 2004, my partner Francisco Javier Ortiz
Franco was murdered, also at the hands of
the
Arayano-Felix Cartel.
He had just made a report in Z, about how
the structure of the
cartel was integrated, and how they had a
relationship of complicity with the State
Prosecutor's Office.
I think it was one of the things that most
affected Don Jesús' life, obviously after
his attack.
Because he even thought that maybe it was
necessary to close Z, that how many more
lives would he
want to understand that in Mexico he
couldn't do what we were doing.
The journalists themselves have tried to
get the government to pass laws saying,
you know, a crime against a journalist is
a
federal crime.
But this has all been very ineffectual and
so the journalists have to be very careful
what kind
of information they're revealing about the
drug cartels.
We have newspapers that are investigating
drug trafficking in Mexico.
Of course, the life of a journalist
affects not only the family of that
journalist or the
media in which that journalist worked, but
many others.
Censorship in Mexico is basically a result
of the threat of
violence imposed by the drug cartels and
the failure of the government to provide
minimal
safety guarantees for reporters and the
media to do the work without fear of
reprisal.
Killing of journalists is not collateral
damage.
The government is being complicit in not
investigating the murderers of
journalists.
The Mexican government has failed to
preserve freedom of expression in this
country
because sometimes freedom of expression is
uncomfortable for them.
Stop recording.
There was an accident.
That's why there was an accident.
I'm a communication man.
I'm interested in accidents.
Calm down.
Don't get in my way again.
If you want things to be good, don't do it
again.
I'm going to stop recording.
Of course I won't if this is live.
Why don't you record the kidnappings we
do?
Me too.
What do you want to stop?
At Z, we are very clear that our
commitment is to the readers, nothing
more.
We believe that no one, not the corrupt
government, not the abusive government,
not the drug traffickers, not the
kidnappers, not the
criminals, have the right to find a means
that society is supporting.
Freedom, solidarity and the support we
have.
Having seen the pervasive climate of
violent crime and impunity, I could not
simply let myself be killed under
some lonely streetlight.
In September 2008, I left Mexico with my
family and went to Vancouver, Canada.
I'm still alive and I'm fortunate for
that.
But I feel the pain of having fled my
country and my profession.
I now have a part-time job as a janitor,
the only work I could find after 14 months
of unemployment.
We are alive, out of the crossfire, but
having loved so much.
Thank you.
There have been 20 journalists murdered in
Russia since 2000 when President Putin
came first to office.
And in other of those cases have those who
commissioned the crimes been punished.
Journalists are targeted for their work
when in the process of reporting
The murders of journalists have become
less frequent in Russia.
Attackers have favored severely injuring
and even maiming journalists on the job.
One prominent example of this new and
frightful tendency is the case of
journalist Mikhail Beketov.
Of course, there were warnings.
First, his dog was killed here in the
yard.
Then the car was blown up.
And the last one.
The newspaper was called Khinkinskaya
Pravda.
This newspaper was published twice a
month.
Mikhail was the head of the department.
He wrote the truth.
He was expecting an attack from minute to
minute.
But he made a
miscalculation.
Two killers were sent to Misha.
They processed him right on the territory
of his house.
They beat him.
They broke his legs, his arms, his head.
It's a miracle that he survived.
He was lying there for days in the cold.
And only because he was a soldier, a
paratrooper, a commander, and only because
of his
powerful health, did he survive.
He was a towering figure before the
attack, and he had been long at odds with
the local administration.
He would not relent, and he paid the most
severe price.
Even though he's alive now, he cannot do
his job anymore.
When you were coming here, were you coming
from Himok?
From the Khimki side, right?
This is exactly the whole forest they
wanted to let go under the root.
Khimki is a criminal region completely
under the control of the local
authorities.
In the
city of Khimki, where the highway that is
built by Putin's friends and brothers in
Attenberg with the help of the French
largest
investment bank should pass.
People stood up for the protection of the
forest.
And we say that the highway can go to
another place.
Vladimir Strebchenko is the mayor of the
city of Khimki.
Apparently, he was interested in the sale
of land for the construction of this road.
And everything is spinning from here.
these terrible crimes against journalists
and so for years these crimes go
uninvestigated and
punished.
Vladimir Putin is an ex-KGB officer.
So there's a whole kind of shadowy world
of these operatives, some of whom, many of
whom are now linked into
business, some of whom have links with
organized crime.
So if you want to do a business deal or
you want to take someone out, you have
access to people who can do it for you.
So they didn't have a client?
There was a client, yes.
And how do you think they will find a
client?
Well, they say that the client is unknown.
What is the state of the
investigation?
It's in a deadlock.
Why can't they get the client?
Because it's my own guess.
There are high-ranking officials involved.
Anna Politkovskaya was without a doubt
Russia's bravest investigative journalist
but she was most famous for her
reporting on Chechnya.
At one point she was abducted there, but
then released.
She was threatened several times.
You have to be on the run all the time.
Change clothes, stay alert, simply to do
your job as a journalist, to collect
information from both sides.
The kind of terrible irony is that she was
someone who faced death so many times in
Chechnya, and then she was actually
murdered
in the lobby of her apartment block in
Moscow.
She was just stepping into the elevator
and someone surprised her and shot her.
The case is being investigated, but they
are being
investigated for murder.
And as a rule, the conflict between the
journalist and the client is at the client
level.
And the client of this murder is not in
the case.
The New Newspaper, the independent
newspaper based in Moscow, is probably...
the newspaper which knows most of what it
is like to lose colleagues to work-related
murders.
Natasha Estimirova was killed.
She wrote a lot after her death.
And now, in fact, Chechnya is a closed
zone for most of the
readers.
Nastya Baburova was killed.
A young girl was shot.
There was even a trainee in the staff.
Stas Markilov, who has done many things in
the editorial department, also did
anti-fascist cases, that is, he
persecuted nationalists, racists.
You have a top leadership in the country
that, while they give lip service to free
expression, they really don't believe in
it.
When Vladimir Putin comes on the record
and says days after murder of Anna
Politkovskaya that
her role in society was insignificant,
when he says that her journalism didn't
matter,
that gives an extremely damaging message
that the journalism that she was doing
doesn't matter.
To this day we don't know who ordered the
gunman to her doorstep.
People sort of were guessing pretty much
from the beginning who might be
responsible, but it's very difficult to
pin these people down and it's very
difficult to prove responsibility.
I think that the hair of my correspondent
is not worth the facts that he will get.
Apparently, it's time for me to leave this
job because...
I am very afraid, and I am fairly afraid,
I have portraits hanging behind my back,
of the risks for my people, and I explain
to
everyone that no one's tears of your
parents are worth any material, even the
most sensational one, that you will
bring to the newspaper.
Moscow police are investigating a brutal
attack on a correspondent with Russia's
Kommersant newspaper.
Oleg Kashin was fiercely beaten near his
home and is now in...
I was speaking not as a investigator, but
as a commentator who called fools fools,
and so on.
It probably irritated many people and, in
principle, it was not such a big surprise
for me.
What story were you involved in when the
attack happened?
There were several stories.
The first one that came to my mind when I
woke up was the story of the Khinkin
forest.
It's a forest in and of itself, but
everyone doesn't care.
All these painful points have come
together in this place.
First of all, the environment is good in
Daugava.
Secondly, it is the impudence, the
impudence and the impunity of the
authorities, which are ready to go to
violence and deception to achieve their
goals.
Mr.
Kashin is currently in a very critical
condition, in an induced coma.
One video from a CCTV camera which
actually captured the attack itself leaked
into the internet on Monday.
The police have already strongly
criticized...
And I approach this cage, a man turns
around, looks at me, throws a bouquet on
the ground and throws a very good boxer's
punch in the jaw, which I fall.
I've already seen the rest on video,
because apparently I lost consciousness
from the first blows.
After that, the second man, whom I didn't
see, appeared from a dark corner with an
iron rod in his hands.
And with this rod he hit me, I tried to
count, but more than half a hundred hits
on the head, especially on the mouth area.
That is, my jaw was broken.
And they deliberately broke my leg,
apparently, so that I wouldn't go
anywhere.
When I woke up, doctors told me that my
arm was bandaged, that one finger was
amputated and another one
was broken.
Naturally, I had a romantic version that
they broke my finger so that I wouldn't
write.
We argue with colleagues, investigators,
whether they
wanted to kill or not.
Probably, they didn't want to, because if
they wanted to kill, they would have
killed.
The fact that my story caused a surge of
indignation among my colleagues, exactly
such a unity, it was insanely surprising
to me when I came to myself, because I
could not imagine that there was, at
least, some solidarity among journalists.
Irritation was accumulated, irritation,
indignation with all the murders.
I think it's just a kind of natural
phenomenon.
This generation, this class is standing up
for freedom of speech.
Unfortunately, the problem of our
government It's not about our
journalism.
They don't need journalists for the
knowledge they have and for the leadership
of the country.
Show me the document Here I am showing you
the document.
Press, Echo, Moscow and the Communist
Party.
The role of the journalist is to provide
transparency, to tell what's really
happening, to uncover the true story, to
cut behind the
propaganda, to cut behind the government
line.
The main goal of this publication was to
inform the population about the official
madness.
We protested against the increase in the
rent.
After the rally ended, I asked people to
accompany us, because we were afraid that
the
protesters could behave inadequately.
I was the last one to go.
Three people came to me, they were in the
police station.
Later we found out that they were police
officers.
Without explaining the reason, they broke
my arms and started beating me.
Luckily, there were just 3,000 witnesses
who were not indifferent.
They just clung to the ring and began to
push the policemen away.
Grandmothers with sticks were pushed away.
Who could have done it?
I lost consciousness several times,
because they hit me on the head, when they
realized that they could not lead me away.
But the most painful place
is the head.
It remains a question who beat me.
These faces are still not officially
identified.
Moreover, the police officer who attacked
me, the most important one who hit me on
the head, got promoted and became deputy
chief immediately after the incident with
my beating.
Whenever enterprising journalists are
slain or silenced or drowned and
marginalized,
everybody suffers.
Here's an example of an extremist case
that was filed against me.
How many papers did I have to write?
Three examinations.
For journalists, the law allows them to be
removed from their activities by accusing
them of
extremism.
says that in Russia...
Russia is especially dangerous to be a
journalist.
Russia is especially dangerous to be
anyone.
I'm not going anywhere with you.
Your actions are illegal.
You are violating my rights.
Extremism is called disagreement with the
opinion of the authorities expressed in
any sharp form.
Like six harmonies stretched to any width
and playing any melody necessary to power.
If I was told in the last minute, don't
write about this and that, then you won't
be able to get your head around it.
I would probably say, go to hell, I would
still write about it, but in principle,
it's just my
stupidity and stupidity, because of
course...
It's not worth it, definitely.
I'd rather give myself back this memory
than write an extra note of truth.
...and for the state, we can say, in such
a period...
It's a measure of a civil society to have
an active, aggressive press.
And when that starts to break down, civil
society starts to break down.
...and now to honor the memory of our
comrades...
Today we...
Can we say that we live in a civil
society?
Of course not.
Our society is shattered today by people
who really
want the progress of our country towards a
free Russia.
And a huge number of people who are
pulling us back to Stalinism, to the
darkest abyss of the Unliberation.
It's clear to everyone.
We will always say that we have democracy,
that our people rule the country.
But if in our places there is such a
vokhanali, such madness of officials,
corrupt officials, bandits,
no one will respect us in the
world.
the investigative journalism is extinct.
Not yet.
But it is an endangered species.
Only takes one journalist to be beaten or
assaulted or murdered for the rest of his
colleagues to think, why am I in this
profession?
I'm not being well compensated for this
profession.
What keeps me going?
Isn't there a easier way of doing, you
know, making a living?
Now I have left the...
Journalists, and, accordingly, in my
opinion, I do not represent a threat for
them.
Messages with threats have stopped coming.
Thank God, no one tried to beat me up with
a car, and the police did not beat me up.
If suddenly I become the editor-in-chief
again and start, God forbid, to condemn
them again in all
the sins, I think there will be the same
scenario.
You see, I worry about my city.
I don't want it to be clean and beautiful.
I don't want to have enough space for all
children in kindergartens.
I want to have roads without pits.
I've always been indifferent.
Unfortunately, it's impossible to work
here.
It's very unreal in places so far.
Do you have any ways to work for
journalists?
Anonymously.
How?
I think the issue of journalist safety is
something which should concern everybody
and not just journalists.
It should concern everybody who cares
about the freedom of speech.
If you could surface some of the bravery
and some of the courage that goes on in
order to tell the world what's happening,
then I think that
society would respond better to the
business of journalism and what we're
trying to do.
Certainly politicians think the media is
incredibly powerful.
Why don't we use some of that power to
support those people who need it, to
support the safety of those people who are
taking all these risks, by ensuring that
there is a penalty more often than not for
killing a journalist.
So we have managed to persuade the United
Nations Security Council to sign up to
article
1738, which sends out a very strong signal
that you can't murder journalists
and hope to get away with it.
The Daniel Pearl Act was passed which said
that the US government really called on
nations to protect journalists and not to
allow something like that to happen.
However, much like the UN resolution is a
statement of intent, it has no real force.
Almost everyone I know who does this has
this sense of mission.
If you are...
in a war zone and see something happen in
front of you that shouldn't be happening.
And you bring that back to where the
policymakers are and they see that and
they change the policy.
You are doing your job.
I am optimistic.
I think that you see spreading around the
world this general desire for the rule of
law and for governments that are more
accountable to their people.
People want information.
They want judicial systems that are
independent.
As that continues, you will see that there
will be accountability for people who
abuse journalists and less
impunity.
It's really common I think for people to
be looking for new sources of information
and I think that that really underscores
and puts
more importance on journalism and how
great the need is.
It's like we need fresh air to breathe.
You know, we need it, we know it when it's
not there, we suffer from its lack, and
we're going to look for it.
I always have a romantic vision of...
I love my job, it's my passion, it's my
life.
But I think our job is also about taking
risks.
So we have to control it, we have to be
very careful, even more careful.
But I don't think we can afford to tell a
country, we're not going there anymore,
goodbye everyone, and we'll call you in a
few years when things get better, to
interview those who have survived.
We can't afford to do that when we're
journalists.
I'm not sure if you can hear me.
It's part of a conversation, it's now
leaning forward.
Not only does it want to know about what's
going on, it wants to influence the
outcome.
So the most humble of person anywhere in
the world with a handheld telephone can
play a part in that
conversation and can influence the
outcome.
Anywhere that there are journalists
working, I think, is actually good for
democracy, good for society, good for the
population at large.
People need to know.
People need to be able to make up their
own minds.
What interests us when we say this is to
say that the press is us because we write,
but it's you because you read it.
And to defend the freedom of the press is
you to defend, it's not us to defend.
Killing of journalists, it's not a
question that is directed to journalists.
This is a question that is directed to
society.
When we put something on the air that
helps someone who had no way to reach the
levers of
power, that's what the Fourth Estate is
all about.
That's why I'm risking my life.